<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet title="Using the X10 Development Toolkit">

<intro>
<description>
This cheat sheet briefly describes how to use the X10 Development Toolkit to
configure the X10DT, create X10 projects, create X10 classes, and use launch
configurations to run and debug X10 programs.
</description>
</intro>

<item title="Configure the X10DT">
<action pluginId="com.ibm.watson.safari.x10"
        class="com.ibm.watson.safari.x10.cheatsheets.actions.OpenX10PreferencesAction"/>
<description>
Before using the X10DT for the first time, you first need to make sure the X10DT
can find certain critical resources that it needs to run.<br/>

Invoke "Window" -&gt; "Preferences" -&gt; "X10", and make sure that the "Common
directory" field points to an existing folder "x10.common" on your hard drive.
Click on the "Browse..." button to bring up a folder selection dialog if not (or
just type in the path directly if you know it).<br/>

Next, make sure that the "Configuration file" field specifies an existing X10
configuration file (e.g. "standard.cfg"). This file will typically reside in
the "etc" sub-directory of the "Common directory" that you specified above. (If
you installed X10 manually from a .zip file, you should have run "ant" in the
"x10.common" directory, which creates a "standard.cfg" file from the settings of
various environment variables (e.g. "JAVA_HOME" and "X10_PLATFORM").)<br/>

Likewise, ensure that the "Compiler template" field specifies an existing folder
(probably named "data") containing the compiler templates. This folder typically
resides within the "x10.compiler" plugin/project. If you manually installed from
a .zip file, type in or browse to the location of the installation directory's
"x10.compiler/data" folder.<br/><br/>

If you installed X10DT using the Eclipse Update Manager, the default settings
should already be correct. If they aren't, you're screwed.<br/>

The remaining options settings on this preference page are not critical; all
X10 functionality should work reasonably with whatever values you enter.<br/>

Note that the configuration file is automatically written by the X10 Preferences
page when a field (such as the "statistics disable") is changed.<br/>
</description>
</item>

<item title="Create an X10 project">
<action pluginId="com.ibm.watson.safari.x10"
        class="com.ibm.watson.safari.x10.cheatsheets.actions.NewX10ProjectAction"/>
<description>
Invoke "File" -&gt; "New" -&gt; "Project" -&gt; "X10 Project".<br/>

Fill out the "Name" field with a unique non-existing project name.<br/>

Most likely, you'll want to accept the default location for the project (i.e. in your
workspace).<br/>

We strongly recommend setting the "Create separate source and output folders" option.
This will place the generated class files in a separate folder from the X10 source.
You may encounter problems in the X10DT with compiling and debugging if you don't select
this option.<br/>

Hit "Finish" when done editing the various fields.<br/>
</description>
</item>

<item title="Create a new X10 Class">
<action pluginId="com.ibm.watson.safari.x10"
        class="com.ibm.watson.safari.x10.cheatsheets.actions.NewX10TypeAction"/>
<description>
Invoke "File" -&gt; "New" -&gt; "X10" -&gt; "X10 Class".<br/>

In the "Source folder" field, you enter both the project in which you would like
the new class to reside, and the source folder within that project that is to
contain the X10 class.<br/>

Usually, there is one source folder per project, as is the case when you follow
the above instructions for creating your X10 project.<br/>

You can type the project name and source folder into the text field, but a much
easier way to do this is to click on the "Browse..." button next to the "Source folder"
field. This will bring up a selection dialog that will allow you to quickly
navigate to the project and source folder you want to use.<br/>

If you want to place the X10 class in a non-default package, enter the package
name into the "Package" field. Again, you can use the "Browse..." next to the
"Package" field to show the list of existing packages in the given project.
At this time, you cannot create a new package from within the "New X10 Class"
dialog; it must already exist.<br/>

Enter the name of the new X10 class in the "name" field, and use the modifier
buttons and checkboxes to specify the visibility and other characteristics of
your class.<br/>

If you wish, enter in the "Superclass" field the fully-qualified name of the
desired base class for your new X10 class, or use the "Browse..." button to
the right to bring up the class selection dialog. Of course, if you leave
x10.lang.Object as the superclass, you can always change the superclass later
by editing the class definition in the source code.<br/>

To add interfaces to the class, click on the "Add..." button to bring up an
interface selection dialog. This will display the list of all interfaces on
the build-time classpath for your project.<br/>

Hit "Finish" when done editing. The source file for the new class will be
open in the editor. You should see the structure of the X10 class source in the
"Outline" view.<br/>
</description>
</item>

<item title="Using the Editor and Outline View">
<description>
You should see keywords highlighted in the source editor, as well as an outline
of the source file's contents in the "Outline" view on the right. The Outline
view shows the types, members and anonymous instances defined in the source code.<br/>

You can navigate to a given source code entity by simply clicking on the corresponding
item in the Outline view. Click on the "+" or "-" controls next to a given item in the
Outline view to expand or collapse the sub-tree rooted at that item.<br/>
</description>
</item>

<item title="Launching your X10 program">
<action pluginId="com.ibm.watson.safari.x10"
        class="com.ibm.watson.safari.x10.cheatsheets.actions.LaunchX10ProgramAction"/>
<description>
</description>
</item>

<item title="Debugging your X10 program">
<action pluginId="com.ibm.watson.safari.x10"
        class="com.ibm.watson.safari.x10.cheatsheets.actions.DebugX10ProgramAction"/>
<description>
</description>
</item>

</cheatsheet>
